<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="cosmic_animated_resize_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2026 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="animated window resize protocol">
    This protocol allows clients to request that the compositor animate
    a resize transition to a target size. The compositor will send
    intermediate configure events to the client for smooth animation.
    
    This is useful for side panels, embedded viewers, and other UI
    elements that need smooth resize transitions.
  </description>

  <interface name="zcosmic_animated_resize_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for animated resize requests">
      This interface allows clients to create animated resize controllers
      for their toplevel surfaces.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy this manager object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_animated_resize">
      <description summary="get animated resize controller for a surface">
        Create an animated resize controller for the given wl_surface.
        The surface must be the root surface of an xdg_toplevel.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zcosmic_animated_resize_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zcosmic_animated_resize_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="animated resize controller">
      This interface allows clients to request animated resize transitions.
      The compositor will animate the window from its current size to the
      target size by sending intermediate configure events.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this controller">
        Destroy this animated resize controller.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="resize_to">
      <description summary="request animated resize to target size">
        Request the compositor to animate a resize from the current window
        size to the specified target size. The compositor will send
        intermediate xdg_toplevel.configure events with sizes along the
        animation path.
        
        The client should render at each intermediate size for smooth
        animation. When the animation completes, a 'done' event is sent.
        
        If width or height is 0, that dimension will not be changed.
      </description>
      <arg name="width" type="int" summary="target width in logical pixels"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int" summary="target height in logical pixels"/>
      <arg name="duration_ms" type="uint" summary="animation duration in milliseconds"/>
    </request>

    <request name="resize_to_with_position">
      <description summary="request animated resize with target position">
        Request the compositor to animate a resize from the current window
        geometry to the specified target size and position. The compositor
        will animate both size and position smoothly.
        
        The client should render at each intermediate size for smooth
        animation. When the animation completes, a 'done' event is sent.
        
        If width or height is 0, that dimension will not be changed.
        The x and y coordinates specify the target window position in
        output-local coordinates.
        
        If the window is maximized/fullscreen, the position will be stored
        and used when the window is restored to normal state.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="target x position in logical pixels"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="target y position in logical pixels"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int" summary="target width in logical pixels"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int" summary="target height in logical pixels"/>
      <arg name="duration_ms" type="uint" summary="animation duration in milliseconds"/>
    </request>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="resize animation completed">
        Sent when the animated resize has completed and the window has
        reached its target size.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="cancelled">
      <description summary="resize animation was cancelled">
        Sent if the animation was cancelled (e.g., user manually resized
        the window during animation, or another resize_to was requested).
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
