<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="cosmic_exclusive_mode_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2026 Playtron

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="exclusive window mode protocol">
    This protocol allows a client to request exclusive mode for its window.
    When exclusive mode is enabled, the compositor will minimize all other
    toplevel windows on the same output. When exclusive mode is disabled
    or the window is closed, the compositor will restore the previously
    minimized windows.
    
    This is useful for applications like AI assistants or system overlays
    that need to temporarily hide all other windows to provide a clean
    focused interface.
  </description>

  <interface name="zcosmic_exclusive_mode_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for exclusive mode requests">
      This interface allows clients to create exclusive mode controllers
      for their toplevel surfaces.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the manager">
        Destroy this manager object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_exclusive_mode">
      <description summary="get exclusive mode controller for a surface">
        Create an exclusive mode controller for the given wl_surface.
        The surface must be the root surface of an xdg_toplevel.
        
        Only one exclusive mode controller can be active per surface.
        Creating a second controller for the same surface is a protocol error.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zcosmic_exclusive_mode_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zcosmic_exclusive_mode_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="exclusive mode controller">
      This interface allows clients to enable or disable exclusive mode
      for their window. When exclusive mode is enabled, all other toplevel
      windows on the same output are minimized. When disabled, they are
      restored.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy this controller">
        Destroy this exclusive mode controller. If exclusive mode was
        enabled, this implicitly disables it and restores minimized windows.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_exclusive">
      <description summary="enable or disable exclusive mode">
        Enable or disable exclusive mode for this window.
        
        When enabled (exclusive = 1):
        - All other toplevel windows on the same output are minimized
        - The compositor tracks which windows were minimized by this request
        - This window remains visible and gains focus
        
        When disabled (exclusive = 0):
        - Windows that were minimized by this exclusive mode are restored
        - Windows minimized by user action remain minimized
        
        The compositor will send an 'enabled' or 'disabled' event in response.
      </description>
      <arg name="exclusive" type="uint" summary="1 to enable, 0 to disable"/>
    </request>

    <event name="enabled">
      <description summary="exclusive mode was enabled">
        Sent when exclusive mode has been successfully enabled.
        The count indicates how many windows were minimized.
      </description>
      <arg name="count" type="uint" summary="number of windows minimized"/>
    </event>

    <event name="disabled">
      <description summary="exclusive mode was disabled">
        Sent when exclusive mode has been disabled, either by client
        request or because the window was closed/destroyed.
        The count indicates how many windows were restored.
      </description>
      <arg name="count" type="uint" summary="number of windows restored"/>
    </event>

    <event name="failed">
      <description summary="exclusive mode request failed">
        Sent when an exclusive mode request could not be fulfilled.
        This can happen if another window already has exclusive mode,
        or if the compositor policy prevents exclusive mode.
      </description>
      <arg name="reason" type="string" summary="human-readable reason"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
